how can you tell
if the monk or
your teacher or a teacher knows what
they are talking about
what's the standard that one should
follow
well the first thing to recognize is
that you don't have
the fully accurate standard because if
you did you wouldn't need a teacher
so the second standard then is to to be
honest with yourself
to see whether you're choosing or
considering following a certain teacher
because um you're really kind of understanding
um you're really kind of understanding
or at least
it's making you think and making you
want to understand what he's teaching
or because you're inspired by his
demeanor by the energy or aura or whatever you
by the energy or aura or whatever you
might think you might be perceiving
is it just uplifting you in sense of
inspiration so emotionally pleasing to
hear that
or is it because it really intrigues you
and you know even scares you in a way
and outlines something that you
recognize as work to be done
so if you re if you check why you're
inclined to this teacher that teacher if
you clarify this
then the next step would be okay so
these things that are being taught
if i'm understanding them correctly if i
were to understand them
fully to the extent they're being taught
is that would that result in dispassion
disenchantment uh sense restraint naturally or does it
uh sense restraint naturally or does it
bring
passion to increase and so on and then
if it's
if it's increasing passion for example
or is it because i'm misunderstanding it
or is it because no i fully understood
and the teacher confirms that's exactly
what he teaches
and yet i'm not free from passion
so your goal individually for every
individual themselves should be
free from passion aversion and delusion
indolence free from craving
so you follow the teaching for that goal
you don't forget that that's the goal
the goal is not
inspiration the goal is not to be like
that teacher or this teacher the goal is
to be free from passion and craving for
yourself
and that's that's the standard you
should use
is gratitude an appreciation for life
the result of contemplating death
correctly or understanding death
correctly
it depends what you mean by appreciation
for life
whether you mean being content with
little then yes if you mean valuing sensuality
then yes if you mean valuing sensuality
more
no means you're not practicing
mindfulness or death correctly
so if you if if you are if your
appreciation of life
is expressed through valuing things
through your senses more
and being being more um enamored with
them so to speak giving them more value
so to speak giving them more value
because everything will come to pass so
it's it's much more important much more
special then you're not really
practicing mindfulness of death
correctly because if you do it correctly
it will result in dispassion
that means that even physical discomfort
and sense deprivation
you will be content with
because you have no passion towards
either you have no passion towards
prolonging pleasure
and you have no passion towards trying
to get rid of the pain
will you enjoy the present moment more
defined enjoyment like the enjoyment
mean not being bothered by it
or the joy may mean enjoying that which
comes to the present moment which is
inevitably going to be on the level of
the senses
so either way if you're enjoying your
senses and sense objects more as a
result of your
sense restraint and your your practice
of mindfulness of death means you're not
doing it sufficiently let's say like
that you do it sufficiently this passion will
you do it sufficiently this passion will
arise concerned
peril will become visible in even a
moment of enjoyment of senses
because it's incompatible with death and
with image of death and with mindfulness
of death
so the only time you can appreciate
senses more on account to practice
mindfulness of death is
lapsing from mindfulness of death which
is why you appreciate the senses more
but in your mind you still think you're
established in the perception of
mindfulness of death but that's not the
case because passion has a reason in
your experience
so what you have is the idea of the
practice of mindfulness of death but
that idea is not the actuality